Hello, everyone!
皆さん こんにちは！
I bring you warm greetings
統治体と米国のベテル家族からの
温かいあいさつをお伝えします
from the Governing Body
and the United States Bethel family.
We want you to know
that we love you all very much,
私たちは皆さんのことを心から愛し
心配しています
we’re concerned about you,
and we pray for you each and every day.
皆さんのために毎日祈っています
コロナウイルスは私たちにますます
大きな影響を及ぼしています
We know that more and more
of you are being affected
by the coronavirus pandemic.
You can’t go to work.
仕事にも 学校にも行けません
You can’t go to school.
You can’t go to the Kingdom Hall
or preach from house to house.
王国会館にも 伝道にも行けません
Some of you have lost your jobs,
仕事を失い 家族を養えるだろうかと
頭を抱えているかもしれません
and you have no idea how
you are going to be able to feed your family.
Others have family members who live far away.
遠くで独り暮らしをしている
家族のことを考えると
There’s no one else in the house.
心配でたまらないかもしれません
They’re worried about them.
残念なことに
この病気で大切な人を亡くして
And sadly, some are mourning
the loss of loved ones
つらい思いをしている方も
おられるでしょう
who have been victims of the disease.
We want you to know
that our hearts ache for you.
残された方たちのことを思うと
本当に心が痛みます
We’re so sorry for your loss.
Now, these are very stressful times,
今は大変な時期です
but it’s important to remember one thing:
でも ぜひ覚えておきたいのは
No friend of Jehovah
エホバの友は決して独りではない
ということです
is ever truly alone.
Through his holy spirit, Jehovah can help us;
エホバは聖なる力によって
私たちを支えてくださいます
he can sustain us
even if there’s no one else in the house.
独りで暮らしていてもです
Another way Jehovah is helping us
またエホバは 優しい牧者を用いて
助けてくださいます
is by means of caring shepherds.
And this is in line
with the promise that he himself made.
そうすると約束してくださっています
We’re going to read Jeremiah 23:4,
エレミヤ 23:4を見てみましょう
この預言は
今どのように実現しているでしょうか
and you’ll see how this prophecy
is being fulfilled today.
I’m just going to read a part of it.
一部をお読みします
エホバはこう約束しています
Here’s the promise Jehovah made:
that he was
going to “raise up . . . shepherds
「私は 彼らをしっかり世話する
牧者たちを立てる
who will really shepherd them.”
And then at the end it says:
［飛んで 彼らの］誰も失われない」
“None [of them] will be missing.”
Well, can you see how that promise
この言葉は現代の長老たちに
どのように当てはまりますか
is being fulfilled today in the elders?
長老たちがどんなことをしてくれて
いるか考えてみてください
Just think of all the work
our elders are doing
to make sure that we don’t miss out
on spiritual food, for example.
私たちが神からの教えを
得られるよう頑張っています
They are arranging for us
to tie in to congregation meetings,
オンラインで会衆の集会を開いたり
牧羊を行ったり
they set up shepherding calls
using videoconferencing,
野外奉仕のための集まりを
計画したりしています
they arrange for meetings for field service,
また 電話や手紙で伝道できるよう
区域を準備しています
and they make sure
we have telephone territory
and letter-writing territory.
Of course, these shepherds
もちろん長老たちは
皆さんの健康も気遣っています
are also concerned
about your physical well-being.
So from time to time,
they may also check in on us
それで 食べ物や 薬や その他
必要なものがちゃんとあるかどうか
to make sure that we have basic food items,
尋ねてくれたりするかもしれません
medications, and other necessary things.
If they do that, don’t be shy:
そういう時は 遠慮しないで
必要な物を伝えてください
Let the elders know your needs.
They may also provide practical suggestions
on how you can protect your health.
健康を守るのに役立つアドバイスも
してくれるでしょう
Now, as you can imagine,
when the pandemic broke out,
感染が拡大する中 長老たちの頭には
いろんな疑問が浮かびました
the elders had a lot of questions.
They’d never dealt with this before.
これまでにない状況だったからです
And suddenly, they needed to do all kinds
of things that they hadn’t done before:
したことがないようなことを
急にしなければならなくなりました
set up videoconferencing accounts,
ビデオ会議のアカウントを作り
learn how to use new apps like Skype®
スカイプやズームなどの
アプリの使い方を覚えて
and Zoom—what’s that?—
and become familiar with how
会衆の集会を最初から最後まで
オンラインで行うようになりました
to organize
an entire congregation meeting online.
It’s been a huge task for our brothers,
大変な仕事だったと思います
and we want to commend them
for the excellent job they’re doing.
長老の皆さん
本当によく頑張りましたね
初めは疑問だらけだった長老たちに
The elders had a lot of questions,
but through his organization,
エホバは組織を通して
必要な指示を与えてくださいました
Jehovah provided the direction they needed.
And an experience
from Canada will bring this out.
この点を示すカナダでの経験があります
Let’s watch a video
in which Brother Warren Shewfelt,
ビデオを見てみましょう
カナダの支部委員会で奉仕している
a member of the Canada Branch Committee,
ウォーレン・シューフェルト兄弟が
話してくださいます
explains what happened in Canada.
In the face of the coronavirus threat,
コロナウイルスが広がる中
支部の近くのある会衆の長老団は
a body of elders near the Canada branch
recently met to determine
集会をどのように行っていくか
についての会合を持ちました
how to go forward with congregation meetings.
They had so many questions
政府が集会の規模を規制する中で
about how to balance
the spiritual needs of the brothers
いったいどうすれば
兄弟たちを強められるでしょうか
with government regulations on gatherings.
エホバに導きを祈りました
They prayed to Jehovah for guidance.
いろいろ話し合っても なかなか
良い方法が見つかりません
But as their meeting went on,
it still wasn’t clear to them how to proceed.
その時ある兄弟が
自分のタブレットを見て
And then one of the brothers
noticed on his electronic device
支部から長老団宛の指示が
来ていることに気付きました
a letter from the branch
with instructions to the elders.
そこには知りたかった点が
全て載っていて
As they read through it,
it answered all their questions
気付いていなかったことも
説明されていました
and even some they hadn’t anticipated.
They viewed this
as Jehovah’s answer to their prayers,
祈りに対する
エホバからの答えだと思いました
but now they had
less than 24 hours to prepare
でも ビデオ会議システムを使っての
初めての集会まで
their first-ever congregation meeting
by videoconference.
24時間もありませんでした
祈りつつ 支部からの指示を
1つずつ実行しました
Prayerfully, they followed
the instructions step-by-step,
and the next evening,
the whole congregation gathered
そして次の日の夜 ビデオ会議での
集会を開くことができました
for a meeting by videoconference.
出席者は100％を超えました
The attendance was well over 100 percent,
and one of the families who were
in attendance wrote to the elders:
長老たちはある家族から
こんなメッセージを受け取りました
“We are so grateful for all the effort
「兄弟たちが頑張って
くださったおかげで
エホバからの励ましを
得ることができました
“to provide this
much needed spiritual food live.
しかもライブで！
“It was exactly what we needed.
本当に必要としていたものでした
ありがとうございます！」
Thank you.”
What an encouraging experience that was!
本当に励みとなる報告でした
Thanks, Warren.
We really appreciate it.
ありがとうございました
この経験を聞いて
And, you know, it reminds me
of what the prophet Isaiah foretold
イザヤ 65:24の預言を
思い出しました
at Isaiah 65:24:
そこにはこうあります
“Even before they call . . . , I will answer;
「彼らが呼び掛ける前に私は答え
彼らがまだ話しているうちに
私は聞き入れる」
while they are yet speaking, I will hear.”
When we think of caring elders,
our circuit overseers come to mind
長老たちに加えて
巡回監督にも感謝できます
because they’re often a vital link
between the branch
災害時などに 支部と会衆を結ぶ
重要な役割を果たしてくださるからです
and the congregation when disaster strikes.
2010年 私は妻と共に
ハイチを訪問しました
That reminds me of an experience
my wife and I had back in 2010.
I was assigned to do
a shepherding visit to Haiti
ハイチの兄弟たちを牧羊するためです
about 10 days after a tremendous earthquake
30万人以上が犠牲になった大地震の
10日ほど後のことです
took hundreds of thousands of lives.
And sadly, 154 of our brothers
also lost their lives.
残念なことに
154人の兄弟姉妹が亡くなりました
Well, I met with the traveling overseers
in the country,
何人かの巡回監督に会いましたが
and I learned that some of them
had lost members of their own family.
その中には自分の家族を
亡くした人もいました
でも 先頭に立って
救援活動を行っていたので
But they were at the forefront
of the rescue effort,
so they hadn’t had time
to mourn their own loss.
悲しんでいる時間もありませんでした
They were still looking
for survivors of the quake.
生存者を捜し続けていたのです
So, what did Jehovah say?
エホバが言われた通りです
“I will raise up . . .
shepherds who will really shepherd them.
「私は 彼らをしっかり世話する
牧者たちを立てる
None [of them] will be missing.”
［彼らの］誰も失われない」
And those shepherds in Haiti
were going to make sure
ハイチの牧者たちは
兄弟姉妹が誰一人失われないように
頑張っていました
that none of their brothers
and sisters were missing.
この流行病の中 巡回監督たちは
今も会衆のために一生懸命働いています
Do you know that our fine traveling overseers
are continuing to serve congregations
as best they can during this pandemic?
How is that possible?
どのようにですか
In this encouraging video report,
Brother Paul Echon,
次のビデオでは 遠隔地の会衆が
どのように世話されているかについて
who is a member
of the Philippines Branch Committee,
フィリピンの支部委員である
tells how even remote congregations
are being cared for.
ポール・エイチョン兄弟が
話してくださいます
This is interesting.
では どうぞご覧ください
Let’s watch.
A circuit overseer in the Philippines
ある巡回監督が
巡回区の端にある2つの会衆を
wrote regarding his experience
using the videoconferencing app Zoom
ズームを使って訪問したことについて
報告してくれました
to visit two
of the remotest congregations in his circuit.
Normal travel to these islands by small boat
太平洋に面したそれらの島に行くには
may take between five to eight hours,
海の状態にもよりますが ボートで
5時間から8時間くらいかかります
depending on sea conditions
and the size of waves from the Pacific Ocean.
Because of the COVID-19 pandemic,
新型コロナウイルスの影響で
travel restrictions to Patnanungan
パトナノンガン島とホマリグ島への
渡航が制限されました
and Jomalig islands were implemented.
The circuit overseer and his wife
巡回監督と妻は 3月後半の2週間に
prayed fervently to Jehovah,
asking for a possible means
to still visit the congregations
何とかそれらの会衆を訪問
させてください と熱烈に祈りました
the last two weeks of March.
Just days later, they received
a letter from the branch office
数日後 支部から手紙が届き
普段とは違う方法で会衆を
訪問するよう提案されました
about alternative ways
of making congregation visits.
This included
the possibility of virtual visits
その方法の1つが
ビデオ会議システムを使って
オンラインで訪問することでした
with the use of online conferencing tools.
The circuit overseer
immediately informed the elders,
巡回監督はすぐに長老たちと連絡を取り
and they excitedly tested
their newfound means of communication.
長老たちはドキドキしながら
その方法を試しました
The visits were a success!
訪問は大成功でした！
The brothers and sisters were so thankful
兄弟姉妹はたいへん喜び
エホバからの愛を実感しました
and really felt Jehovah’s love for them.
Reflecting on his experience,
the circuit overseer said:
巡回監督はこの経験を振り返って
こう言っています
「コロナウイルスがどれほど広まろうと
“It is obvious that no coronavirus
全能の神エホバはご自分に仕える
人たちを必ず力づけてくださいます
“can prevent our Almighty God, Jehovah,
“from providing encouragement
to his servants today.
私も妻も 兄弟たちがエホバを
心から信頼し続けるよう助けたいと
“We are determined more than ever
to help and encourage
“the brothers to continue trusting
in Jehovah completely,
いっそう強く思うようになりました
“as mentioned at Psalm 91:2, which says:
詩編 91:2にある通り
‘You are my refuge and my stronghold.’”
エホバは『私の避難所
私のとりで』なのです」
What did we read at Jeremiah 23:4?
エレミヤ書には何とありましたか
“None [of them] will be missing.”
「［彼らの］誰も失われない」
Jehovah knows where all his sheep are,
エホバはご自分の羊の
居場所を知っていて
and he arranges for them to be cared for.
きちんと世話してくださいます
エイチョン兄弟 フィリピンの
兄弟姉妹にぜひよろしくお伝えください
Thanks, Paul.
And please give our warm love and greetings
to our brothers in the Philippines.
皆さんを心から愛しています
We love them all very much.
さて ここまでで何を学べましたか
So, what do we want to take away
from this brief discussion?
2つあります
Two points: First, we believe that Jehovah
まず
エホバはどんな時にも ご自分の組織を
必ず導いてくださる ということです
will continue to guide his organization
every step of the way.
組織が兄弟たちを守るために
And it’s been faith-strengthening
to see how, at times,
当局より1歩も2歩も進んだ指示を
与えているのを見ると
the organization has been
one or even two steps ahead
of the authorities
in giving direction to protect the flock.
信仰が強められます
So that’s the first point:
それで最初のポイントは エホバは
必ず組織を導く ということです
Jehovah will continue
to direct the organization.
第二に エホバは優しい牧者である
長老たちを用います
Second, what is one of the means
by which he will do that?
By providing loving shepherds
to carry out that direction.
長老たちは組織からの指示を実行します
そして長老たちを指導している
イエスはこう言っています
And over them is the One who said:
“I am the fine shepherd;
「私は立派な羊飼いです
“the fine shepherd surrenders his life
立派な羊飼いは羊のために
命をなげうちます」
in behalf of the sheep.”
Brothers and sisters,
take good care of yourselves.
兄弟姉妹の皆さん
くれぐれも体に気を付けてください
Don’t take chances.
危ないことはしないでください
Obey the instructions
of “the superior authorities.”
「上位の権威」の指示に従いましょう
ベテルでは当局の指示に従うよう
細心の注意が払われています
We at Bethel are extremely conscientious
about following
the guidelines we’ve received.
So if the authorities tell you
to stay home, stay home.
外出しないようにと言われたら
外出しないでください
Practice social distancing.
人との距離を保ちましょう
Now, keep up-to-date with the news,
but don’t obsess.
最新の情報に付いていくのは大切ですが
見過ぎないようにしましょう
Don’t watch it too much.
It can be just too discouraging.
気持ちがめいってしまうからです
Now, what season are we in?
今は 1年で一番大切な
記念式の時期です
Memorial season.
So, what should be the real focus
of our thoughts at this time?
私たちは何に思いを向けるべきですか
The incredible gift of the ransom,
贖いという素晴らしい贈り物
エホバ神の愛
the love of Jehovah God,
the love of Christ Jesus.
そしてキリスト・イエスの愛です
Those things should be
the object of our thoughts.
こうしたことを考えるべきです
孤独に感じる時や
ストレスを感じる時には
And when you feel alone or stressed-out,
repeat to yourself the heart-cheering words
ヘブライ 13:5の
心温まる言葉を思い出してください
that we find at Hebrews 13:5:
“I will never leave you,
「私は決してあなたを離れず
決してあなたを見捨てない」
and I will never abandon you.”
「私は決してあなたを離れず
決してあなたを見捨てない」
“I will never leave you,
and I will never abandon you.”
私たちは皆さんを愛し
皆さんのことを祈っています
Be assured of our warm love and prayers.
From the World Headquarters
of Jehovah’s Witnesses,
エホバの証人の世界本部から
JW Broadcasting®でした
this is JW Broadcasting®.